<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>True news from Reading: or, an exact relation of the Prince of Oranges victory over the Kings forces there, on the nineth of this instant December, 1688. In a letter to a friend.</title>
            <author>T. I.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1688</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 4 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 2 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">B03794</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing I16</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R178389</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">52612178</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 52612178</idno>
            <idno type="VID">179473</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. B03794)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 179473)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English Books, 1641-1700 ; 2790:5)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>True news from Reading: or, an exact relation of the Prince of Oranges victory over the Kings forces there, on the nineth of this instant December, 1688. In a letter to a friend.</title>
                  <author>T. I.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>1 sheet ([1] p.)   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for G.L.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>in the year 1688.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Caption title.</note>
                  <note>Signed: T.I.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the National Library of Scotland.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>James --  II, --  King of England, 1633-1701.</term>
               <term>William --  III, --  King of England, 1650-1702.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  History --  Revolution of 1688 --  Sources.</term>
               <term>Reading (England) --  History --  17th century --  Sources.</term>
               <term>Broadsides --  England --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-09</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-09</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-10</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-10</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <body>
         <div type="letter">
            <pb facs="tcp:179473:1"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb facs="tcp:179473:2"/>
            <head>
               <hi>True News from Reading:</hi> OR, An Exact Relation of the Prince of <hi>Oranges</hi> Victory over the Kings Forces there, on the Nineth of this Inſtant <hi>December,</hi> 1688.</head>
            <head type="sub">In a Letter to a Friend.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>My Good Friend.</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>HEre we have been in the midſt of theſe late hurries, the King's Armies March<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing backward and forward by us; then the Princes, and now many March<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing back again to Winter Quarters; 'tis in vain to write of matters back<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward, now things are carryed ſo forward; only I obſerve no Printed Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per hath given a Tollerable Account of the Memorable Engagement lately at <hi>Reading;</hi> all I have ſeen are Falſe and Fooliſh, I ſuppoſe none Printed True, or of any worth: Take this as the moſt Exact, my ſelf being near the Spot, and knowing the whole from Eye Witneſſes; The Kings Army, the Rere Guard, having left <hi>Reading</hi> upon the Approach of the <hi>Princes</hi> Van-Guard, about Seven Troops of Horſe and Dragoons of <hi>Scotch</hi> and <hi>Iriſh,</hi> came back again on <hi>Sat<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rday</hi> the Eighth Inſtant, and there kept ſtrict Guard; the Town be<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ng in great fear of Plunder, Fire, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> But a certain Gentleman ſent Three Meſſengers to <hi>N<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>wberry,</hi> to the Princes Army, to come away and Save the Town; at firſt they were taken for Spies, but bringing proof they were good Men, Orders were given for Two Troops to March at Two of the Clock in the Morning; they they came on very ſlowly all the way, that they might be the more Service<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able in Action: The Kings Soldie<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s had ſet a Sentinel on the Church-Tower, who by firing a Gun, gave notice of their approach (but they came not the great Road, and ſo were not ſeen till very near) ſo Trumpets ſounded, Drums beat, and they ſtood ready; but then immediately the Dutch came in, Riding Furiouſly through ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral Streets, holding their Bridle-Reins on their Little Fingers, their Piſtols on both Hands lying cloſe flat down on their Horſes, Crying, <hi>Hollow, Boys, Hollow;</hi> (at which there was a great Shout in the Town and, <hi>Away Women, away Women;</hi> ſo they charged the <hi>King</hi>'s Souldiers as they found them; Twelve Charged about Two Hundred in the Market-Place; Six leapt their Horſes into St. <hi>Mary</hi>'s Church-Yard over the Stone Steps, and drove out the Dragoon Muſqueteers that lined the Church-Yard-VVall, and others in the Church-Yard; the People being at Church all this while: Thus they Charged every where ſo Furiouſly, that the Kings Soldi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers Ran, and they purſued, Killing ſome, Taking others; they Killed about Eight<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teen, VVounded ſeveral, took about Sixty Horſes; they Purſued them ev'n to <hi>Twiford</hi> Pariſh, where lay a Regiment or more: One <hi>Dutch</hi> Cornet was Kill'd (his Horſe be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Shot under him, then ſeveral Firing upon him) and one Common Trooper: All the ways were ſpread with Boots, Hats, Coats, Swords, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> of the Kings Soldiers that fled; ſome came about Twelve of the Clock to our <hi>Town</hi> without Shoes, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Onthe Twelfth Inſtant I ſaw the Cornet's <hi>Funeral</hi> after the Martial Manner: Three Colours were taken, one of <hi>Iriſh Dragoons,</hi> and two of <hi>Scotch Horſe;</hi> the <hi>Town</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ooks on it as a VVonderful Deliverance; for they ſhew'd themſelves Impatient for the coming of the Princes Army, and ſome of the Wounded Soldiers of the King's Army have declared, that as ſoon as Church was ended, they were to have Killed the People, Plundred for themſelves, and to have ſet fire on the Houſes; But <hi>Eſt Deus <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n Coelis qui Providus omnia Curat.</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Yours, T. I.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="colophon">
            <p>
               <hi>London:</hi> Printed for <hi>G. L.</hi> in the Year 1688.</p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
